Finding Aid for Gunnar Birkerts papers 1930-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gunnar Birkerts papers
1930-2002
Birkerts, Gunnar.
Michigan-based architect, founder of Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, professor in the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Urban Planning. The collection is comprised of four series: Personal papers, Professional papers, Faculty papers, and Project files. Personal papers includes biographical information, family photographs, early architectural drawings, and course notebooks and project drawings completed while a student at the Technische Hochschule Stuttgart. Professional papers includes transcripts and notes of speeches, lectures and seminars (many of these are also available on audiotapes; some are available on videocassettes). Also included are correspondence, awards, travel diaries with conceptual drawings, newspaper and journal articles and photographs. Faculty papers include course and other materials relating to his career as professor at the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Urban Planning. Project files contains textual files, photographs, and conceptual drawings associated with 122 of the buildings and projects designed by Birkerts. Scanned images of some conceptual drawings are available on-line.
02103 Aa 2
11 linear feet
1912 drawings in 11 drawers architectural drawings
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Gunnar Birkerts (donor # 8285 ) in January 1998. Subsequent accessions have been received
The papers are open to research, with the exception of restricted materials in Box 11 including travel diaries and student related material from Birkerts' tenure as a faculty member at the University of Michigan.
The conceptual drawings for a number of individual projects described in the Projects series have been digitized and are available online in the Bentley Library Image Bank. Direct links to individual images are provided in the contents list or searches can be done directly in the Image Bank. For some of the digitized images Birkerts has retained the original drawings.
Gunnar Birkerts is an internationally acclaimed architect of the last half of the twentieth century who has been recognized for his expressive forms, his simplification of detail, his innovative work with surface materials and his effective use of indirect daylight. With his design flexibility and commitment to "finding poetry in building technology," he has pushed beyond the boundaries of the Modern Movement. [1]
Born on January 17, 1925, in Riga, Latvia, Gunnar Birkerts' childhood was steeped in the mythology of his country, as both of his parents, Peteris and Merija Shop Birkerts, were scholars and folklorists who studied the cultural heritage of the Latvian people. Later in his career, Birkerts expressed his gratitude for the rich, architectural and literary images of his homeland which he believed continued to stimulate his creative process.
While attending the first gymnasium in Riga, Birkerts saw an architectural rendering of an upperclassman which inspired him at the age of thirteen to pursue a career in this field. He completed two degrees in engineering and architecture in 1949 at the Technische Hochschule in Stuttgart, where his training exposed him to both Bauhaus and vernacular design. His education in the craft and technology program gave him an understanding of architectural materials and design construction methodology, which would become enduring interests throughout his career.
During his training, Gunnar Birkerts studied the work of Alvar Aalto, Gunnar Asplund, Sven Markelius and Sigurd Lewerentz in Europe and that of Mies van der Rohe, Walter Gropius, Erich Mendelsohn and Marcel Breuer, who had emigrated to the United States. William Lescaze and Frank Lloyd Wright were also of interest to him. However, it was at the U.S. Information Agency Library that he discovered and became attracted to the modern architecture of Eliel and Eero Saarinen with whom he shared northern European roots. Thus, he came to Birmingham, Michigan in December 1949 to seek work with Eero Saarinen, who explained to him upon his arrival in Birmingham, Michigan, that the General Motors Technical Center project was on hold and that no job was available for him. Carrying a letter of recommendation from Saarinen, Birkerts went to Chicago to join the firm of Perkins and Will, which specialized in school architecture. Within a year of his arrival in the United States, he married Sylvia Zvirbulis. Together they had three children, Sven Peter, Andra Sylvia and Erik Gunnar, born in 1951, 1954 and 1967, respectively.
In 1951, Eero Saarinen invited Birkerts to join his firm in Birmingham, Michigan, where he worked with such young architects as Kevin Roche, Robert Venturi and John Dinkeloo. During his four years with Saarinen, he contributed to the General Motors Technical Center in Warren, Michigan and Concordia Senior College in Fort Wayne, Indiana and was the project architect for the Milwaukee County War Memorial. In 1954, he won the young Designer of the Year Award from the Akron Museum of Art. Birkerts was highly impressed by Saarinen's inventiveness and perseverance, qualities which he carried into his own work. He recalls that "in those days it was a battle to bring modern architecture to the world. The whole quest was evangelistic." [2]
Birkerts received American citizenship in 1955, shortly after leaving Saarinen's office to join Donald Grieb in Milwaukee. After one year with Grieb, he was invited by Minoru Yamasaki to work with Yamasaki, Leinweber and Associates, in Birmingham, Michigan. There he was chief designer for the Reynolds Metals Building, the Educational Building at Wayne State University and the Daharan Air Terminal between 1956 and 1959. During this time, he received a number of design awards, including two citations from Progressive Architecture for houses in Wisconsin and first prize in the Cantu, Italy First International Furniture Competition. He was especially proud of the latter because Alvar Aalto, highly esteemed by Birkerts, was one of the jurists.
In 1959, Birkerts became a principal of Minoru Yamasaki and Associates. Despite his admiration for Yamasaki's intuitive creation process, Birkerts thought, "I had listened long enough. My apprenticeship was over. Now it was my turn to speak."[3] Accordingly, he left Yamasaki in 1959 to establish the partnership of Birkerts and Straub. With Frank Straub as project administrator and Birkerts as designer, they produced their first independent projects, including the Schwartz Summer Residence (1960-1962) in Northville, Michigan, the Haley Funeral Home (1960-1961) in Southfield, Michigan, the 1300 Lafayette East Apartments (1961-1963) in Detroit, the Marathon Oil Office Building (1962-1964) in Detroit and the Lillibridge Elementary School Addition (1962-1963) in Detroit.
Birkerts began his twenty-nine-year teaching career at the University of Michigan at this time as well. In 1961, he was appointed assistant professor of architecture, becoming associate professor of architecture in 1963 and professor of architecture in 1969. He was awarded the position of professor emeritus in 1990.
Gunnar Birkerts and Associates was established in 1963 in Birmingham, Michigan, when the architect left his partnership with Frank Straub. The 1960s were prolific years for the practice, as Birkerts designed buildings which contained the "bold forms, space before structure, minimal detailing, stratified walls and daylight in interior spaces"[4] which were the hallmarks of his work during this decade. Among his many important buildings of this period were the University Reformed Church (1960-1964) in Ann Arbor, Michigan, the Detroit Institute of Arts - South Wing Addition (1964), the Fisher Administrative Center (1964-1966) at the University of Detroit, the Lincoln Elementary School (1965-1967) in Columbus, Indiana, the Freeman Residence (1964-1966) in Grand Rapids, Michigan, the Tougaloo College Campus Master Plan (1965) in Tougaloo, Mississippi, the Tougaloo College Dormitories and Library (1966-1972) and the Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis (1967-1973).
During the 1970s, Birkerts continued his exploration of glass and metal as surface technologies. He was also an early advocate for the containment of urban sprawl with his Subterranean Urban Systems Study of 1974, for which he received a Fellowship Grant from the Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts. In 1970, he was elected a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects, and he received a Gold Medal from the American Institute of Architects, Detroit, in 1975. He was also honored by an appointment as Architect in Residence at the American Academy in Rome in 1976. A few of his many notable buildings of this decade are the Contemporary Arts Museum (1970-1972) in Houston, the Dance Instructional Facility (1970-1976) at the State University of New York, Purchase, the University of Michigan Law School Addition (1974-1981) in Ann Arbor, the United States Embassy Office Building (1975, project) in Helsinki, Finland, the Duluth Public Library (1969-1980), the Museum of Glass (1976-1980) in Corning, New York, and the University of Iowa College of Law Building (1979-1986) in Iowa City.
Birkerts received many more awards in the 1980s and 1990s, including the Arnold W. Brunner Memorial Prize in Architecture from The American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters (1981) and the first Bruce Alonzo Goff Professorship of Creative Architecture (1990) at the University of Oklahoma. In a poll conducted by The Buildings Journal of 58 architecture academicians in 1982, Gunnar Birkerts was listed as one of the top ten architects of non-residential structures in the nation, along with I. M. Pei, Romaldo Giurgola, Cesar Pelli, Kevin Roche, Philip Johnson, Michael Graves, Charles Moore, Edward Larrabee Barnes and Richard Meier. Among his important buildings of this period are the Ferguson Residence (1980-1983) in Kalamazoo, Michigan, the Cornell University Uris Library Addition (1980-1982) in Ithaca, New York, the Conservatory of Music Library Addition (1986-1988) in Oberlin, Ohio, and the United States Embassy Office Building (1987-89) in Caracas, Venezuela.
In 1997, Birkerts dissolved Gunnar Birkerts and Associates. He is continuing his practice of architecture from his studio in Bloomfield Hills. Now in the fifth decade of his prolific career, Birkerts is designing the Joint Library of the City of San Jose and San Jose State University in California, the first institution in the country to combine the repositories of a university and a city under one roof. Such other recent works as the Ohio State University College of Law Addition (1988-1993) in Columbus, the Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art and Design (1991-1994) of the Kansas City Art Institute, and the National Library (1989 - in progress) in Riga, Latvia are testament to the innovation, monumentality and freedom of Birkerts' "expressive architecture."[5] The National Library exemplifies Birkerts' powerful use of metaphor which has characterized his work throughout his career and has made his buildings among the most distinctive of the twentieth century.
_______________________
Notes
1) Gunnar Birkerts, Gunnar Birkerts: Process and Expression in Architectural Form (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,1994), 32.
2) Robert Benson, "An Interview with Gunnar Birkerts," Inland Architect (Jan./Feb.1986): 31.
3) Kay Kaiser, The Architecture of Gunnar Birkerts (Washington, D.C.: The American Institute of Architects Press, 1989), 13.
4) Ibid., 15.
5) Kay Kaiser, "World Architecture Profile: Gunnar Birkerts," World Architecture, 36:26.
The Gunnar Birkerts Collection offers researchers the opportunity to study the personal, professional and faculty papers and conceptual sketches of one of the masters of American modern architecture, whose career spans the second half of the twentieth century. The collection encompasses 11 linear feet of Birkerts' student work, notes and transcripts of speeches, lectures and interviews, video and audio tapes, writings, correspondence, awards, travel diaries, academic course materials, photographs and project records. Perhaps the greatest significance of this collection lies in its presentation of over 1900 drawings of 122 buildings and projects by the architect's own hand, many of which are valuable, early conceptual sketches.
In its pairing of narrative and visual documents, the Gunnar Birkerts Collection offers a rich perspective on the architect himself, illuminating his views on the creative process and the resulting conceptual designs which have defined his expressive architecture over his illustrious fifty-plus-year career. The Gunnar Birkerts Collection is the architect's deeply personal legacy. He recognizes that, while some of his buildings may be demolished over time, his original conceptual designs on paper are conserved here for future generations to study and enjoy. To this end, he has endowed the Gunnar Birkerts Collection to ensure that his drawings will be preserved and that his place in architectural history can be studied and understood.
The Gunnar Birkerts Collection is comprised of four series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Faculty Papers and Project Records. The narrative and visual documents in these series illuminate the full breadth of the architect's life and work, from his early years as a student at the Technische Hochschule in Stuttgart, Germany in the 1940s to his career in Michigan as an internationally acclaimed architect, esteemed design professor and global lecturer from the early 1950s to the present.
Subjects:
Birkerts, Gunnar.; Architects--Michigan.; Gunnar Birkerts & Associates.; Architecture--Design and plans.; Architecture--United States.; Architecture, Modern--20th century.; Architectural design.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Urban Planning.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.
- Personal Papers
  The Personal Papers consists of a small biographical file compiled by Birkerts and his wife, Birkert's first architectural drawings; his student notebooks and drawings, and a small group of family photographs. Birkerts first two architectural drawings, renderings of a gas station and house, produced when he was 17 years of age, document his early understanding of modern architecture in 1942. The course notebooks and project drawings, completed while Birkerts was a student at the Technische Hochschule from 1944 to 1949, illuminate the educational foundation of his architectural career and show his incipient interest in furniture as well as building design. Two important photographs of Birkerts with his mother in Riga at the ages of four and five are also found in this series.
  - Biographical Information
    - Biographical Outline Prepared by Gunnar & Sylvia Birkerts, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Gunnar Birkerts Architects, Inc. Website print-out, 03/25/2002 (Box 1)
  - First Architectural Drawings, 1942
    - Renderings Showing Birkerts' First Understanding of Modern Architecture at Age 17
      - Perspective of Shell Gas Station., undated (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
      - Perspective of House., 1942 (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Student Work at Technische Hochschule, Stuttgart, Germany, 1944-1949
    - "Schrifttumsverzeichnis fur Architektur-Studierende" (Student Reading List), Winter Semester,. Notebook with drawings of student projects, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - "Statik I" (Structural Engineering) Notebook, Winter-Spring Semesters, 1947. Course notebook with calculations and drawings (Box 1)
    - "Siedlungswessen" (Village Planning), 1948. Course notebook with drawings (Box 1)
    - Furniture Designs Submitted to International Competition, Museum of Modern Art, 1948., 8 photographs prints of chair and settee perspectives, elevations;details; 9 negatives 1-1/4x2-inch (Box 1)
    - Student Project Drawings., 74 negatives 1-1/4x2-inch (Box 1)
    - Student Project Models., Five 3-1/2x4-1/2-inch photographic negatives of projects and three 3-1/2x4-1/2-inch glass negatives of final "Diploma Arbeit" (Box 1)
  - Student Furniture and Building Designs at Technische Hochschule, Stuttgart, Germany, 1947
    - Architectural Drawings
      - Moebelbau und Innenarchitektur der Vorstand [for] Professor A. G. Schenck
        - Plans, Elevations and Sections of Tables, Bookcases, Lamps Sofas and Chairs., 1947 (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
      - Zweigesch Doppelhaus
        - Plans, Elevations, Sections and Details of House., 1947 (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Photographs, 1920s-1950s
    - Photos (Box 1)
- Professional Papers
  The Professional Papers series encompasses nine subseries relating to Birkerts' career accomplishments as an architect, lecturer and writer over a 50-year period. These subseries include Transcripts and Notes of Speeches, Lectures and Seminars, Transcripts of Interviews, Audio-Visual Materials which correspond to many of the transcripts, Writings, Publications, Correspondence, Awards and Honorary Academic Affiliations, Travel Diaries with Conceptual Drawings, Newspaper and Journal Articles, and Photographs.
  - Transcripts and Notes of Speeches, Lectures and Seminars
    Within the large Professional Papers series, the Transcripts and Notes of Speeches, Lectures and Seminars subseries contains materials related to over 150 presentations given by Birkerts during his career. These transcripts and notes document Birkerts' professional and artistic beliefs, design philosophy and creative process. The subseries is arranged in three further sub-subseries describing the venues of Birkerts' presentations: Academic, Professional and Public, and Dedications. The Academic sub-subseries contains speaking notes and transcripts of the speeches and lectures given by Birkerts to students and faculty at various academic institutions. The Professional and Public sub-subseries includes similar material for addresses given by Birkerts to his professional colleagues as well as to the general public. Comments made by Birkerts at the dedications of a few of the buildings which he designed make up the Dedications sub-subseries. Researchers should note that specific building projects tend to be mentioned in the speeches and lectures occurring between the times of a building's design and completion. For example, Domino's Farms is discussed quite frequently in lectures given from 1984 through 1985. These three sub-subseries contain lectures which can be heard on corresponding audiotapes or videotapes (marked with an * or a #), which are listed in the Audio-Visual Materials subseries. The researcher should also be aware that additional lectures and speeches can be found in the Sources Used for Publication subseries.
    - Academic Institutions
      - Speech Note Cards, 1965-1976; undated
        - Lawrence Technological University, February 6, 1965 (Box 1)
          *
        - University of Kentucky, December 2, 1965 (Box 1)
        - University of Arkansas, April 10-11, 1969 (Box 1)
        - University of Michigan, February 26, 1970 (Box 1)
        - Rice University and University of Texas, February 1971 (Box 1)
        - University of Michigan, December 4, 1971 (Box 1)
        - North Dakota State University, February 9, 1972 (Box 1)
        - Rennselaer Polytechnic Institute, February 23, 1976 (Box 1)
        - Five speeches, undated (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan Wallenberg Symposium Panel on "Architecture as a Humane Art,", March 16, 1972 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan Brown Bag, October 1976 (Box 1)
      - Rhode Island School of Design, January 1977 (Box 1)
      - Texas A & M University, February 3, 1977 (Box 1)
      - New York Institute of Technology, April 25, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Kent State University-"Appropriate Architecture, Architecture of No Style, Architecture of Response,", September 22, 1977 (Box 1)
      - University of Nebraska, November 10, 1977 (Box 1)
      - University of Florida-Gainesville and Columbia University, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Speech Templates, 1977 (Box 1)
      - University of Texas at Austin, November 15, 1978 (Box 1)
      - Autonomous University of Guadalajara Seminar, February 20, 1979 (Box 1)
      - University of Detroit School of Architecture-"The Philosophy and Methodology of Gunnar Birkerts,", March 23, 1979 (Box 1)
      - Louisiana State University, September 25, 1979 (Box 1)
      - Arizona State University and University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, October 6, November 1, 1979 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous Lecture Notes, circa 1970s (Box 1)
      - Georgia Institute of Technology and Auburn University, February 19-20, 1980 (Box 1)
      - Southern California Institute of Architecture, California Polytechnic State University and University of California, Berkeley, May 6-8, 1980 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan Seminar-"Knowing Yourself,", September 1980 (Box 1)
      - SUNY Buffalo and University of Kentucky, September 29, October 6, 1980 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan-"Man the Builder,", circa 1980 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan-Michigan Law Library Justification, circa 1980 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan Brown Bag-"Design Methodology,", February 9, 1981 (Box 1)
      - Pratt Institute, December 4, 1981 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan, "Design Methodology II,", 1981 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan, circa 1981 (Box 1)
      - University of Oklahoma, April 6, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Ball State University, April 14, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Cranbrook School, November 4, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Texas A & M University and University of Michigan, November 18, 1982 (Box 1)
      - Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture, Knoxville Charette, Fall 1982 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan Seminar-"Symbolism and Metaphor" (goes with tape "Metaphor, Symbolism and Color"), circa 1982 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan Seminar, circa 1982 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous Lecture Notes, circa 1982-1983 (Box 1)
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 1983
      - University of Illinois-Plym Lecture Series
        - Lecture I, January 24, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Lecture II, January 31, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Lecture III-"Metamorphosis of Design Methodology,", February 14, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Seminar I-"You and Your Mind, Knowing Yourself,", February 18, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Seminar II-"Daylight and Energy,", circa February, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Bob DeHaven's Theory Seminar, April 19, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Faculty Colloquium I, January 26, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Faculty Colloquium II, February 15, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Faculty Colloquium III, March 15, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Forum I, February 9, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Forum II, February 23, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Forum III, March 14, 1983 (Box 1)
        - Forum IV, April 13, 1983 (Box 1)
      - Iowa State University, May 9, 1983 (Box 1)
      - New York Institute of Technology, November 16, 1983 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan-"Next Architecture,", February 13, 1984 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan-"Next Architecture-You and Your Mind/Methodology,", March 5, 1984 (Box 1)
      - University of Arkansas Charles L. Thompson Memorial Lecture, April 12, 1984 (Box 1)
      - University of Idaho and Washington State University Seminars, April 26, 1984 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan-T. S. Monaghan Lecture, October 1, 1984 (Box 1)
      - Virginia Tech-"Departures,", November 7, 1984 (Box 1)
      - University of Michigan-T.S. Monaghan Lecture-"Concepts and Manifestations,", November 12, 1984 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous Lecture Notes, circa 1984 (Box 1)
      - University of Notre Dame-"Next Architecture,", March 8, 1985 (Box 1)
      - Andrews University, April 18, 1985 (Box 1)